Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs, 1888-1944; Series VIII; 1.75; (4 boxes)
  - MARINETTI PHOTOGRAPHS
    - World War I
      - 68. Rome. FTM on balcony of his Piazza Adriana apartment. Castel Sant'Angelo in background., ca. 1925 (Box 49, Folder 1940)
      - 69. Rome. FTM before Boccioni's Footballer (portrait photo). Photographer Scharankoff of Rome. Inscribed on verso: "Marinetti davanti il 'Footballer' di Boccioni.", ca. 1925 (Box 49, Folder 1940)
      - 70. Rome. FTM, BCM, Russolo and Casella with an actress and two unidentified men. [LMB suggests this is following a performance at the Bragaglia Theatre.], ca. 1925 (Box 49, Folder 1940)
      - 71. Scene from FTM's play, I Prigionieri. Stage design by BCM. Inscribed on verso: "I prigionieri" and "Benedetta" as well as measure- ments for publication., 1925? (Box 49, Folder 1940)
      - 72. Rome. FTM, BCM, Prampolini and Tato in the Futurist section of the Biennale. Typescript attached to bottom of photo: "Benedetta, Marinetti, Prampolini, Tato, at a Futurist exhibition." [Related photo reproduced in Giovanni Lista, Balla (1982), p. 348.], 1925 (Box 49, Folder 1940)
    - Mt. Etna Camping Trip, August 1925
      - 73. Men washing and shaving. FTM, Jannelli and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 74. Duplicate of n. 73. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 75. Men washing and shaving. FTM and another man. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 76. Duplicate of n. 75, made into a postcard. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 77. Duplicate of n. 76. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 78. Men washing and shaving. FTM and two other men. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 79. Duplicate of n. 78. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 80. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 81. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 82. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 83. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 84. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 85. Men washing and shaving. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 86. FTM washing. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 87. Duplicate of n. 86. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 88. FTM shaving. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 89. Tents and men seen from a distance. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 90. Tents and men seen from a distance. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 91. Tents and men seen from a distance. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 92. Tents and men seen from a distance. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 93. Men talking near tent. (Box 49, Folder 1941)
      - 94. At the door of a tent. FTM and BCM. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 95. Duplicate of n. 94. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 96. Duplicate of n. 94. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 97. Duplicate of n. 94. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 98. Duplicate of n. 94. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 99. Duplicate of n. 94. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 100. At the door of a tent. FTM and BCM. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 101. At the door of a tent. FTM and BCM. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 102. Duplicate of n. 101. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 103. At the door of a tent. FTM, BCM, Jannelli and two men. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 104. Duplicate of n. 103, stamped on recto. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 105. At the door of a tent. FTM, BCM, Jannelli and two men. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 106. In the forest. FTM, BCM, and another man and woman. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 107. In the forest. BCM with man and woman in n. 106. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 108. Discussion outside tent. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 109. Duplicate of n. 108, made into a postcard. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 110. Discussion outside tent. FTM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 111. Duplicate of n. 110, made into a postcard. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 112. FTM speaking to an informal group outdoors while BCM and Jannelli take notes. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 113. FTM, Calzini and Jannelli seated before a tent. Inscription: "nell'attendamento di Monte Monaco." (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 114. Duplicate of n. 113, stamped on recto. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 115. Duplicate of n. 114. (Box 49, Folder 1942)
      - 116. Excursion on mules. FTM and BCM on mules. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 117. Excursion on mules. FTM and woman on mules, other people nearby. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 118. Excursion on mules. Woman on mule, other people in background. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 119. Excursion on mules. Woman on mule, other people in background. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 120. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 121. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 122. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 123. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 124. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 125. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 126. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 127. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 128. Excursion on mules. Group of riders. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 129. Excursion on mules. Riders at a quarry. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 130. Excursion on mules. Riders at a quarry. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 131. Excursion on mules. Riders at a quarry. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 132. Excursion on mules. Riders at a quarry. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 133. Excursion on mules. Riders at a quarry. (Box 49, Folder 1943)
      - 134. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM and four unidentified men. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 135. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 136. Duplicate of n. 135. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 137. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM, lying at crater's edge, with others. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 138. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM, Jannelli, lying at crater's edge, with others. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 139. Duplicate of n. 138. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 140. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM, Jannelli, lying at crater's edge, with others. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 141. Duplicate of n. 140, reduced and made into a postcard. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 142. Excursion to crater. FTM, BCM and others near a building. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 143. Excursion to crater. Man at edge of crater. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 144. People eating outdoors. FTM and BCM facing each other midway down the table. Jannelli is at the far left. Photo signed by various people and inscribed to FTM. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 145. Duplicate of n. 144. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 146. People eating outdoors. Same group as in nos. 144 and 145. Inscribed. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 147. People eating outdoors. FTM, BCM and others. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 148. People eating outdoors. Group. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 149. People eating outdoors. Group. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 150. Three men seated outside reading newspapers. (Box 49, Folder 1944)
      - 151. Three men seated outside reading newspapers. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 152. People in a truck. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 153. Woman in the distance [BCM?] (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 154. Duplicate of n. 153. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 155. Landscape. Inscribed: "Valle del Bove." (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 156. Duplicate of n. 155. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 157. Landscape. Inscribed: "Cono d'ombre (mattina)." (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 158. Landscape. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 159. Landscape. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 160. Landscape. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
      - 161. Landscape. (Box 49, Folder 1945)
    - General
      - 162. Bologna. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni) and Angelo Caviglioni seated on the floor of a Futurist exhibition. Inscribed on verso: "Tato e Caviglioni alla Esp. futurista di Bologna." [Photo reproduced in Tato RacconTato da Tato (Milan, 1941), fig. 4. This date is published in Lista, Futurisme: Mani- festes - Documents - Proclamations (1973).], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 163. Bologna. Duplicate of n. 162. Inscribed on verso: "I pittori futur- isti Tato e Caviglioni alla Esposi- zione di Bologna," and, in another hand, "ca. 1932-33 Tato & Caviglioni." [See: reference information above.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 164. Bologna. Futurist paintings, sculpture, furniture and parole-in- libertà at a Futurist exhibition as seen in n. 162 and n. 163. Inscribed on verso: "Sala futurista di Tato e Caviglioni." [See: reference inform- ation above.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 165. Bologna. Duplicate of n. 164. [See: reference information above.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 166. Bologna. Casa d'Arte Tato. On back wall, large decorative panel by Tato, Marcia su Roma. [See: Tato, Tato RacconTato da Tato, Milan, 1941, fig. 1.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 167. Bologna. FTM with Tato (center) and Angelo Caviglioni. Inscribed on verso: "Tato e Papa." [Photo processed in Bologna.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 168. Rome. FTM, BCM, Depero (on ottoman), Mazza (behind BCM) and others (from the back, far left) Luciano Folgore, Remo Chiti, and Enrico Prampolini at FTM's apartment. Boccioni's Footballer on wall. [Giovanni Lista, in his Marinetti e le futurisme, dates a related photo 1926.] (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 169. Rome. FTM (behind Mazza), Folgore, Prampolini, Depero (to the left of FTM), BCM and others at FTM's apartment. [See: reference information above.], 1926? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 170. Paris. Scene from FTM's play, Cocktail. Stage set by Prampolini. Inscribed on verso: "Prampolini, Cocktail di Marinetti, Prampolini, Teatro della Pantomima Futurista, Parigi, 1927, Benedetta." (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 171. Modena. FTM in a group of young men. Inscribed on recto: "Modena 9-4- 1927 V.", 1927 Apr 9 (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 172. Modena. FTM seated with a group of young men. Inscribed on recto: "Modena 9-4-1927 Anno V.", 1927 Apr 9 (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 173. Modena. FTM talking in a group of young men. Inscribed on verso: "Arditi di Modena.", 1927 Apr 9 (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 174. FTM portrait photo as an Acca- demico d'Italia., 1929? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 175. Rome?. FTM and other members of the Accademia d'Italia in their uniforms. [This is the date FTM was inducted into the group.] Left to right: Francesco Cilea, Marcello Piacentini, Francesco Copolla, Armando Brasini, Pietro Mascagni, FTM, Umberto Giordano, Ettore Romanoli, Enrico Fermi., 1929 Mar 18? (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 176. Bucarest. FTM with the "Futurists of Bucarest". Inscribed to FTM and autographed by those present on verso. Dated on verso., 1930 May 11 (Box 50, Folder 1946)
      - 177. The Futurist Table. FTM and others seated at table. Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio...Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 178. The Futurist Table. The room before the guests arrived. Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio...Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 179. The Futurist Table. View of the room (with typewriter). Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio...Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 180. The Futurist Table. View of the room (with cogwheel centerpiece). Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio... Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 181. The Futurist Table. View of the room (with horse cartoon on wall). Inscribed on verso: "La tavola futur- ista." Stamped on verso: "Photo- Maggio...Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 182. The Futurist Table. View of the room (with bed). Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio...Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 183. The Futurist Table. View of the room (with "Tavolta la donna" poster). Stamped on verso: "Photo-Maggio... Tunis.", ca. 1931 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 184. Genoa. FTM with a group of Futurists at a formal reception by the city of Genoa. Depero at far right. Inscribed on verso: "Ricevimento dei futuristi in Municipio." Date stamped on verso., 1931 Jul 21 (Box 50, Folder 1947)
      - 185. Rome. FTM and an unidentified man in FTM's apartment in Piazza Adriana. Gerardo Dottori's portrait of FTM and family on the wall behind. [See: related photo and additional information in Giovanni Lista's, Balla (1982), p. 247.], ca. 1932 (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 186. Rome. FTM and BCM in their apart- ment in Piazza Adriana, holding FTM's Parole in libertà futuriste olfattive tattili termiche. Portraits of FTM by Depero (left) and Rougena Zatkova (right) hang on the walls. Photo by Luxardo of Rome., ca. 1932 (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 187. Rome. FTM and BCM in their apart- ment in Piazza Adriana, holding FTM's Parole in libertà futuriste olfattive tattili termiche. Portraits of FTM by Depero (left) and Rougena Zatkova (right) hang on the walls. Photo by Luxardo of Rome (slightly cropped)., ca. 1932 (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 188. Duplicate of n. 187., ca. 1932 (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 189. Naples. FTM at a meeting with other men. [Giovanni Lista reproduces a related photo in his Petrolini (1981), p. 42, and identifies those present as FTM, Libero Bovio, G. Nazzaro, and Cangiullo, at the Circolo della stampa, Naples, 1932.] (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 190. Duplicate of n. 189. [See: reference information above.], 1932? (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 191. Naples. FTM at a meeting, standing and reading. [See: reference information above.], 1932? (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 192. Naples. FTM at a meeting, holding a paper entitled "Premio Roma". [See: reference information above.], 1932? (Box 50, Folder 1948)
      - 193. Trieste. FTM with Bruno G. Sanzin (far right), Fedele Azari? (lower left), and an unidentified man. Inscribed on verso: "papa ed i futuristi." [Photo- grapher's name and "Trieste" in lower right.], 1932? (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 194. Trieste. FTM with Bruno G. Sanzin (left of FTM) and three unidentified men. Inscribed on verso: "Trieste.", 1932? (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 195. Viareggio. FTM with several men at an exhibition. Inscribed on verso: "Con Viani? Viareggio 1932." (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 196. Viareggio. FTM with several men at an exhibition. Inscribed on verso: "Con Viani? Viareggio 1932." (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 197. Sofia, Bulgaria. FTM and BCM in a group. Inscribed on verso: "a Sofia Dicembre [sic] 1932.", 1932 Jan (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 198. FTM and BCM in a car., 1932 Jan (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 199. Sofia, Bulgaria. FTM and BCM in a group. Inscribed on verso: "a Sofia.", 1932 Jan 19 (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 200. Sofia, Bulgaria. FTM and BCM in a group of men, women and children. Typescript attached to photo: "Sofia - Casa degli Italiani A[nno] X.", 1932 Jan 19 (Box 50, Folder 1949)
      - 201. Savona. FTM at the Lito Latta tin factory where the metal covers for his Parole in libertà olfattive tattili termiche were made. Cover designed by Tullio d'Albisola. Inscribed on recto: "S.E. Marinetti all'uscita dello stablim'to. Lito Latta Savona 1-8-1932-X." Inscribed on verso in FTM's hand: "a Savona Lito Latta.", 1932 Aug (Box 50, Folder 1949)
    - Egypt
      - 202. FTM and BCM in front of a pyramid., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 203. FTM and BCM on camels., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 204. FTM and BCM on camels, with guides., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 205. FTM and BCM seated, a man in uniform behind., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 206. FTM in profile before the Sphinx., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 207. FTM on a camel., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 208. Duplicate of n. 204., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 209. FTM and BCM in a group. Photo processed in Cairo., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
      - 210. Postcard., ca. 1933 (Box 50, Folder 1950)
    - General
      - 211. Mantua. FTM and Mino Somenzi in a group at the Mostra Nazionale d'Arte Futurista, which opened on this date in the Palazzo Ducale. [See: related photo in Giovanni Lista, Le Livre Futuriste, p. 127, and in Mino Somenzi, Difendo il futurismo (1938), p. 73.], 1933 May 1 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 212. Mantua. FTM and Mino Somenzi in a group at the Mostra Nazionale d'Arte Futurista, which opened on this date in the Palazzo Ducale. Inscribed on verso: "Mantova." [See: reference information above.], 1933 May 1 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 213. Capri. Negative of Vittoria, Ala and Luce Marinetti. [Removed from a letter from FTM to BCM of this date.], 1933 Sep 14? (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 214. BCM, Vittoria and Ala with one of the five large panel paintings representing Land, Sea, Air, Tele- graphic, Telephonic and Radio Commun- ication, executed by BCM for the Post Office building in Palermo, Sicily., ca. 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 215. BCM, Vittoria and Ala with one of the five large panel paintings representing Land, Sea, Air, Tele- graphic, Telephonic and Radio Commun- ication, executed by BCM for the Post Office building in Palermo, Sicily., ca. 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 216. BCM with one of the five large panel paintings representing Land, Sea, Air, Telegraphic, Telephonic and Radio Communication, executed by BCM for the Post Office building in Palermo, Sicily., ca. 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 217. BCM with one of the five large panel paintings representing Land, Sea, Air, Telegraphic, Telephonic and Radio Communication, executed by BCM for the Post Office building in Palermo, Sicily., ca. 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 218. BCM and a workman with two of the five large panel paintings representing Land, Sea, Air, Telegraphic, Telephonic and Radio Communication, executed by BCM for the Post Office building in Palermo, Sicily., ca. 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1951)
      - 219. Turin. FTM at the Turin Book Fair. Luciano Folgore at the right; Ardengo Soffici at the left helping turn the pages. Inscribed on verso in blue pencil in FTM's hand: "Festa Libro Torino 1934." (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 220. Turin. FTM at the Turin Book Fair. Inscribed on verso in blue pencil in FTM's hand: "Festa Libro Torino 1934." (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 221. Turin. FTM at the Turin Book Fair holding a copy of Poemi Simultanei Futuristi. Inscribed on verso in blue pencil in FTM's hand: "Festa Libro Torino 1934." (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 222. Turin. FTM at the Turin Book Fair., 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 223. Turin. FTM, BCM, Mino Somenzi (with cigarette in mouth), Paolo Buzzi (to the right of Somenzi) and a crowd at the Lingotto Fiat factory. Inscribed on the verso: "Dono dell'Ardita Ling- otto." [See: related photo in Mino Somenzi, Difendo il futurismo... (1938), p. 73.], 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 224. Turin. FTM, BCM, Mino Somenzi and Paolo Buzzi (in beret) in a crowd at the Lingotto Fiat factory. Inscribed on verso. [See: reference information above.], 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 225. Turin. FTM, BCM, Mino Somenzi and Paolo Buzzi in a crowd at the Lingotto Fiat factory. Inscribed on verso: "Dono dell'Ardita Lingotto 1934." [See: reference information above.] (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 226. Turin. FTM in a group at the Lingotto Fiat factory. Inscribed on verso: "Dono dell'Ardita Lingotto 1934." [See: reference information above.] (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 227. Rome. FTM, BCM, LMB, Vittoria and Ala before the huge Italian flag presented to FTM by the government at the Prima Mostra Nazionale d'Arte Futurista., 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 228. Rome. FTM, BCM, King Vittorio Emanuel III, and Mino Somenzi at the Prima Mostra Nazionale d'Arte Futurista, organized by the news- paper Futurismo. [For related photos and more information on this exhibition, see: Mino Somenzi, Difendo il futurismo (1938).], 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 229. Rome. FTM, BCM, King Vittorio Emanuel III, Mino Somenzi and others at the Prima Mostra Nazionale d'Arte Futurista, organized by the newspaper Futurismo. [See: reference inform- ation above.], 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 230. Rome. FTM and King Vittorio Emanuel III at the Prima Mostra Nazion- ale d'Arte Futurista, organized by the newspaper Futurismo. [See: reference information above.], 1934 (Box 50, Folder 1952)
      - 231. Ernesto Thayaht. Inscribed on verso: "All'amico Marinetti con vivissimo strina e affetto. Thayaht. 1934 Aprile." (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 232. Reggio Emilia. FTM with several men leaving the Futurist exhibition at the Municipal Theatre. Inscribed on verso: "All'uscita dalla Mostra Futurista nel Teatro Municipale Reggio Emilia. 28-4-XII.", 1934 Apr 28 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 233. Carrara. FTM and others at the marble quarry. Stamped on verso and the date inscribed on verso., 1934 May (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 234. Genova. FTM in a group at the opening of the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista, held in the Palazzo Ducale. Behind the group is Prampolini's Ritmi ascensionali delle forze fasciste. Depero is at the far right. Inscribed on verso: "2o Convegno Naturista Futurista Genova." [see the catalogue of this exhibition for a full account of the opening including a list of those present.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 235. Genova. FTM in a group at the opening of the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista (Palazzo Ducale). Inscribed on verso: "2o Convegno Naturista Futurista Genova." [See: reference information above.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 236. Genova. Audience at the opening of the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista (Palazzo Ducale). Inscribed on verso: "2o Convegno Naturista Futurista Genova." [See: reference information above.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 237. Genova. FTM at the opening of the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista (Palazzo Ducale). Behind is Prampolini's Ritmi ascensionali delle forze fasciste. Inscribed on verso: "2o Convegno Naturista Futurista Genova." [See: reference information above.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 238. Genova. FTM, in uniform, standing in a group of men at the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista (Palazzo Ducale). Inscribed on verso: "Genova Plastica Murale." [See: reference information above.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 239. Genova. Crowd at the Prima Mostra Nazionale di Plastica Murale per l'Edilizia Fascista (Palazzo Ducale). Prampolini's Ritmi ascensionali delle forze fasciste in the background. Inscribed on verso: "Genova Plastica Murale." [See: reference information above.], 1934 Nov 14 (Box 51, Folder 1953)
      - 240. Naples. FTM leaving for Ethiopia. BCM behind him. Inscribed on verso in LMB's hand: "FTM and BCM when FTM left for Ethiopia." Photo processed in Naples., 1935 Oct (Box 51, Folder 1954)
    - Ethiopia, 1935 October - 1936 April
      - 241. FTM seated in a tent, smiling. (Box 51, Folder 1954)
      - 242. FTM with officers. Inscribed on recto: "a S.E. Marinetti a ricordo d'una visita che lui fatta al 174o Batt. cc nv. nella zona di Ende Marian ______ [illegible]. Seniore Morsero". Inscribed on verso: "(da destra a sinistra) S.E. Marinetti, Seniore Morsero - Com.te 174o Bta. cc. nv., Gen. Somma - Com.te la "Ferrea", Om. Pace, ________ [illegible] Boufatti - Capo di S.M." (Box 51, Folder 1954)
      - 243. FTM with another officer and natives. Inscribed on verso: "Le LL.EE. il Generale Somma comm. Umberto- Comandante la 2o Divisione CC.RR. '28 Ottobre' e il Seniore F.T. Marinetti - alla inaugurazione del mercato di Abbi-Addi (Tembien)," and "A.O.I. Anno XV," and "Coletti Severo Corso della Vittoria, 29 Novaro." (Box 51, Folder 1954)